Tibet
Marist Archives and Special Collections
- Tibet, 2.1.3.5
  - Tibet: Out of This World: Across the Himalayas to Forbidden Tibet by Lowell Thomas, Jr. [illustrations], 1949; 2 (Box 1536)
    - Caption: [pages 240-241] Dad and the rescue team. Front row: Indian Major A. K. bose, nurse Emily Bateman, Dad, Roy Bisbee. Rear, right: Dr. Pal, 6
    - Caption: [page 243] Here the "Rockefeller of Tibet," elder statesman Tsarong Shape, stands to be photographed with his wife and married daughter. Born the son of a humble artisan, Tsarong has risen to a position of wealth and power Verso: Tsarong Shape, richest man in Tibet, 7
    - Caption: [page 243] Here the "Rockefeller of Tibet," elder statesman Tsarong Shape, stands to be photographed with his wife and married daughter. Born the son of a humble artisan, Tsarong has risen to a position of wealth and power Verso: Tsarong Shape, richest man in Tibet, 8
    - Caption: [page 243] Here the "Rockefeller of Tibet," elder statesman Tsarong Shape, stands to be photographed with his wife and married daughter. Born the son of a humble artisan, Tsarong has risen to a position of wealth and power Verso: Tsarong Shape, richest man in Tibet, 9
    - Caption: [page 246] A truly magnificent view of the Potala, "the Palace of the Gods," snapped from the top of nearby Iron Hill. The city of Lhasa proper is out of the limits of this photograph, extending beyond the right side, 10
    - Caption: [page 251] One of the many treasures of the Potala is this fabulous image of the Great Fifth Dalai Lama, who made Lhasa the capital and began building the Potala. The image is of solid gold. Before it is an offering of butter, 11
    - Caption: [page 251] One of the many treasures of the Potala is this fabulous image of the Great Fifth Dalai Lama, who made Lhasa the capital and began building the Potala. The image is of solid gold. Before it is an offering of butter, 12
    - Caption: [page 257] Shaped in curves strange to western eyes, this is the gold-encrusted mausoleum of a departed Dalai Lama. Some of these tombs rise for the whole height of the palace, their summits the gold pagodas on the roof, 13
    - Verso: Shaped in curves strange to western eyes, this is the gold-encrusted mausoleum of a departed Dalai Lama. Some of these tombs rise for the whole height of the palace, their summits the gold pagodas on the roof, 13-verso
    - Caption: [page 257] Shaped in curves strange to western eyes, this is the gold-encrusted mausoleum of a departed Dalai Lama. Some of these tombs rise for the whole height of the palace, their summits the gold pagodas on the roof, 14
    - Caption: [page 259] Everything in this palace chapel is of solid gold-except the red-robed monk, and the offerings of silk scarves, butter and grain. Not the design of the elaborate golden vessel and of the supporting dragon, 15
    - Caption: [page 263] Iron Hill, overlooking Lhasa, is a popular place for making offerings of prayer flags and incense to the gods. The nonchalant raven at the right knows he has nothing to fear; birds and animals are not molested in Tibet, 16
    - Caption: [page 263] Iron Hill, overlooking Lhasa, is a popular place for making offerings of prayer flags and incense to the gods. The nonchalant raven at the right knows he has nothing to fear; birds and animals are not molested in Tibet, 17
    - Caption: [page 265] If the painting is unusually fine it may be blessed by the handprint of the Dalai Lama or the Panchen Lama, in red upon its back. As in early European religious painting, the artist may put in a small self-portrait, 18
    - Caption: [page 265] If the painting is unusually fine it may be blessed by the handprint of the Dalai Lama or the Panchen Lama, in red upon its back. As in early European religious painting, the artist may put in a small self-portrait, 19
    - Caption: [page 265] If the painting is unusually fine it may be blessed by the handprint of the Dalai Lama or the Panchen Lama, in red upon its back. As in early European religious painting, the artist may put in a small self-portrait, 20
    - Caption: [page 267] A view of spreading Sera Gompa, the second largest monastery in Tibet. In the past, the monks of Sera Gompa have been troublesome to the government at Lhasa, sometimes supporting Chinese hegemony, 21
    - Caption: [page 271] A ration of barley flour is doled out to the monks at Sera Gompa, before they crowd into the prayer hall. Their red robes are picturesque but also greasy and tattered, as they are washed only once during a year, 22
    - Caption: [page 271] A ration of barley flour is doled out to the monks at Sera Gompa, before they crowd into the prayer hall. Their red robes are picturesque but also greasy and tattered, as they are washed only once during a year, 23
    - Caption: [page 275] One of the narrow alleys between the buildings of Drepung Gompa, which is built in tiers on the side of a hill. The monastery, seen from afar, resembles a medieval city, and these alleys confirm that impression, 24
    - Caption: [page 277] The central portion of the world's largest monastery, Drepung Gompa, which is occupied by ten thousand Yellow Hat trapas and lamas. We met Drepung's abbots in a room under the top of the red-collared building, 25
    - Caption: [page 283] To eighteenth-century missionaries, as to us, the Potala was a thrilling spectacle. The royal dwellers in the sacred palace were often tolerant toward western priests, who sought to turn their people to Christianity Verso: The Potala in Lhasa; 1000 rooms, golden domes, no elevators, 26
    - Caption: [page 283] To eighteenth-century missionaries, as to us, the Potala was a thrilling spectacle. The royal dwellers in the sacred palace were often tolerant toward western priests, who sought to turn their people to Christianity Verso: The Potala in Lhasa; 1000 rooms, golden domes, no elevators, 27
    - Caption: [page 289] Radio operator Reggie Fox and his Tibetan wife, educated in India, 28
    - Caption: [page 289] Radio operator Reggie Fox and his Tibetan wife, educated in India, 29
    - Caption: [page 289] Henry Harrer and Peter Aufschnaiter explain their route into Tibet, 30
    - Caption: [page 289] Henry Harrer and Peter Aufschnaiter explain their route into Tibet, 31
    - Caption: [page 289] Henry Harrer and Peter Aufschnaiter explain their route into Tibet, 32
  - Tibet: Out of This World: Across the Himalayas to Forbidden Tibet by Lowell Thomas, Jr. [illustrations], 1949; 3 (Box 1536)
    - Caption: [page 297] Midway up Potala's stone steps, Dad talks to Henry Harrer, one of four Europeans in Tibet. We heard that Pro-Chinese Tibetans were dragged by their heels down these stairs to death, or flung from the roof, 1
    - Caption: [page 297] Midway up Potala's stone steps, Dad talks to Henry Harrer, one of four Europeans in Tibet. We heard that Pro-Chinese Tibetans were dragged by their heels down these stairs to death, or flung from the roof, 2
    - Caption: [page 301] The village headman supplied yaks, mules and donkeys for a day's march. Each day we had to make new arrangements for transportation, with a mule driver to return the animals to previous day's starting point, 3
    - Caption: [page 303] L. T., Sr., homeward bound, at the summit of Karo-La, nearly 17,000 feet high. Less than half an hour after I took this photograph, Dad was to be thrown from his horse in the serious accident that impeded our descent Verso: L.T. and glacier at Karo La, just before the accident. At 17,000 ft, 4
    - Caption: [page 307] "O Lord Buddha, lighten our load!" chanted the bearers of Dad's chair as we made the journey down. Their prayers were answered, too, for on that difficult descent from the mountain heights Dad lost twenty pounds, 5
    - Caption: [page 309] Just over Tang-La, we pause to change Dad's bearers, who carried his chair in teams of four. I am riding the mule. Afternoon clouds have gathered over snow and ice on the 24,000-foot summit of Mt. Chomolhari, 6
    - Caption: [page 309] Just over Tang-La, we pause to change Dad's bearers, who carried his chair in teams of four. I am riding the mule. Afternoon clouds have gathered over snow and ice on the 24,000-foot summit of Mt. Chomolhari, 7
    - Caption: [page 309] Just over Tang-La, we pause to change Dad's bearers, who carried his chair in teams of four. I am riding the mule. Afternoon clouds have gathered over snow and ice on the 24,000-foot summit of Mt. Chomolhari, 8
    - Caption: [page 309] Just over Tang-La, we pause to change Dad's bearers, who carried his chair in teams of four. I am riding the mule. Afternoon clouds have gathered over snow and ice on the 24,000-foot summit of Mt. Chomolhari, 9
  - Tibet: Scrapbook photographs [en route to Tibet - Hawaii], 1949; 4 (Box 1536)
    - [left to right:] Earl Thacker, Duke K [Kahanamoku], Lowell Thomas, "Pop" Peltjanski, 1
    - Verso: [left to right:] Earl Thacker, Duke K [Kahanamoku], Lowell Thomas, "Pop" Peltjanski, 1-verso
    - [left to right: Lowell Thomas, Duke Kahanamoku], 2
    - [Lowell Thomas wearing a lei in Hawaii], 3
    - [Lowell Thomas standing in front of an plane], 4
    - [Lowell Thomas tipping his hat in front of a plane], 5
  - Tibet: Scrapbook photographs [en route to Tibet - Japan], 1949; 5 (Box 1536)
    - [Lowell Thomas boarding plane, waving hatm Pan American World Airways bag], 1
    - 25 July 1949; Radio Commentator in Tokyo: Lowell Thomas dean of American commentators, lecturer and world traveler at the Imperial hotel, Tokyo, Japan. Mr. Thomas is on an extensive tour of East and South East Asia, 2
    - Verso: 25 July 1949; Radio Commentator in Tokyo: Lowell Thomas dean of American commentators, lecturer and world traveler at the Imperial hotel, Tokyo, Japan. Mr. Thomas is on an extensive tour of East and South East Asia, 2-verso
    - 19 Jan 1949; Building Project: The Radio Tokyo Building, Tokyo, Japan, 3
    - Verso: 19 Jan 1949; Building Project: The Radio Tokyo Building, Tokyo, Japan, 3-verso
    - [5 copies] 26 July 1949; Lowell Thomas Visits Japan: Miss Marilyn Moore (Washington, D.C.) Sec. Chief of Foreign Trade and Commerce Div., ESS, interviews Mr. Lowell Thomas, world famous lecturer and globe trotter, over WVTR Radio Tokyo, Tokyo, Japan. This broadcast was beamed to the U. S., 4
    - Verso: 26 July 1949; Lowell Thomas Visits Japan: Miss Marilyn Moore (Washington, D.C.) Sec. Chief of Foreign Trade and Commerce Div., ESS, interviews Mr. Lowell Thomas, world famous lecturer and globe trotter, over WVTR Radio Tokyo, Tokyo, Japan. This broadcast was beamed to the U. S., 4-verso
    - [2 copies] 25 July 1949; Lowell Thomas, dean of American commentators and world traveler in Tokyo, Japan. Mr. Thomas is pointing to the park named after his old friend Gen. Jimmy Doolittle, 5
    - Verso: 25 July 1949; Lowell Thomas, dean of American commentators and world traveler in Tokyo, Japan. Mr. Thomas is pointing to the park named after his old friend Gen. Jimmy Doolittle, 5-verso
    - [5 copies] 25 July 1949; Commentator Visits Gen [General] MacArthur: Mr. Lowell Thomas, Dean of American Radio commentators, lecturer and world travel visits with Gen [General] of the Army Douglas MacArthur, SCAP, at the [?], Tokyo, 6
    - Verso: 25 July 1949; Commentator Visits Gen [General] MacArthur: Mr. Lowell Thomas, Dean of American Radio commentators, lecturer and world travel visits with Gen [General] of the Army Douglas MacArthur, SCAP, at the [?], Tokyo, 6-verso
    - [5 copies] 25 July 1949; Commentator Visits Gen [General] MacArthur: Mr. Lowell Thomas, Dean of American Radio commentators, lecturer and world travel visits with Gen [General] of the Army Douglas MacArthur, SCAP, at the [?], Tokyo, 7
    - Verso: 25 July 1949; Commentator Visits Gen [General] MacArthur: Mr. Lowell Thomas, Dean of American Radio commentators, lecturer and world travel visits with Gen [General] of the Army Douglas MacArthur, SCAP, at the [?], Tokyo, 7-verso
  - Tibet: Scrapbook photographs [Tibet skit], 1950; 6 (Box 1536)
    - Hersey [Hershey], Pa. [Pennsylvania], 1
    - Verso: Hersey [Hershey], Pa. [Pennsylvania], 1-verso
    - At San Diego - Admirals, 2
    - Verso: At San Diego - Admirals, 2-verso
    - At San Diego - Admirals, 3
    - Verso: At San Diego - Admirals, 3-verso
    - At San Diego - Admirals, 4
    - [left to right:] Lowell Thomas, Vice Admiral Calvin T. Durgin, Lowell Thomas, Jr., 5
    - Verso: [left to right:] Lowell Thomas, Vice Admiral Calvin T. Durgin, Lowell Thomas, Jr., 5-verso
    - [Vice Admiral Calvin T. Durgin], 6
    - [left to right: unidentified man, Lowell Thomas, Vice Admiral Calvin T. Durgin, Lowell Thomas, Jr., 7
    - l to r: [left to right:] Adm. [Admiral] W. H. Standley, Lowell Thomas, Adm. [Admiral] R. H. Jackson, 8
    - Verso: l to r: [left to right:] Adm. [Admiral] W. H. Standley, Lowell Thomas, Adm. [Admiral] R. H. Jackson, 8-verso
    - [left to right: Admiral W. H. Standley, Lowell Thomas, Jr., Lowell Thomas, Admiral R. H. jackson, 9
    - [Lowell Thomas Jr., Lowell Thomas, and two unidentified men], 10
    - [Lowell Thomas and four unidentidied men], 11
  - Tibet: Scrapbook photographs, circa 1949 - 1950; 7 (Box 1536)
    - [One woman surrounded by six men], 1
    - [Group of people eating an asian meal], 2
    - [Lowell Thomas and two women], 3
    - [Lowell Thomas and an unidentified woman], 4
    - [Lowell Thomas and a group of people], 5
    - [Lowell Thomas and an unidentified man], 6
    - [Lowell Thomas interviewing an unidentified man], 7
    - [Lowell Thomas interviewing an unidentified man], 8
    - [Lowell Thomas and two unidentified men], 9
    - [Lowell Thomas interviewing a man], 10
    - [Lowell Thomas and an unidentified man], 11
    - [Lowell Thomas standing in front of a Buddha statue], 12
    - [Lowell Thomas and Buddha statue], 13
    - [Fireworks], 14
    - [Fireworks], 15
    - [Fireworks], 16
    - [Large house], 17
    - [Large group entering a house], 18
    - [Woman sitting on an altar], 19
    - [Outdoor stone patio], 20
  - Tibet: Scrapbook photographs, circa 1949 - 1950; 8 (Box 1536)
    - Lowell Thomas, Jr. at White House [with Tibetan scroll presented to President Harry S. Truman], 1
    - Verso: Lowell Thomas, Jr. at White House [with Tibetan scroll presented to President Harry S. Truman], 1-verso
    - Lowell Thomas, Jr. at White House [with Tibetan scroll presented to President Harry S. Truman], 2
    - Verso: Lowell Thomas, Jr. at White House [with Tibetan scroll presented to President Harry S. Truman], 2-verso
    - [Lowell Thomas, Jr. on tour to promote his book, Out of This World: Across the Himalayas to Forbidden Tibet], 3
    - [Lowell Thomas riding a donkey], 4
    - To Mr Lowell Thomas- With my best wishes and happy memory of your visit to Lhasa. From your Sincere Friend, (Rimski) W.N.[?] Kyibute, 5
    - Verso: To Mr Lowell Thomas- With my best wishes and happy memory of your visit to Lhasa. From your Sincere Friend, (Rimski) W.N.[?] Kyibute, 5-verso
    - With best wishes. [?] March 1950 [?], 6
    - Verso: With best wishes. [?] March 1950 [?], 6-verso
    - G. Wand Price, Yahiq 1950. [?], 7
    - Verso: G. Wand Price, Yahiq 1950. [?], 7-verso
    - [Two native (?) men], 8
    - [Portraiot of a woman], 9
    - [Caption: To Mr. Lowell Thomas from Chase Mellen (?)], 10
  - Tibet: Tibetan Homes Foundation, circa 1960s; 9 (Box 1536)
    - A Tibetan with his prayer wheel as he arrived in Delhi with 2,200 other Tibetan evacuees after surviving the Chinese invasion of India, 1
    - Verso: A Tibetan with his prayer wheel as he arrived in Delhi with 2,200 other Tibetan evacuees after surviving the Chinese invasion of India, 1-verso
    - An old Tibetan woman who escaped the Chinese invasion of India and made her way with 2,200 other Tibetan refugees to Delhi. On Tibetan New Year's Day 1963 A.E.C.T.R. (American Emergency Committee for Tibetan Refugees) distributed blankets to the children and others in need, 2
    - Verso: An old Tibetan woman who escaped the Chinese invasion of India and made her way with 2,200 other Tibetan refugees to Delhi. On Tibetan New Year's Day 1963 A.E.C.T.R. (American Emergency Committee for Tibetan Refugees) distributed blankets to the children and others in need, 2-verso
    - Lowell Thomas Home, 3
    - Verso: Lowell Thomas Home, 3-verso
    - One of the dormitories in the Lowell Thomas Home, 4
    - Verso: One of the dormitories in the Lowell Thomas Home, 4-verso
  - Tibet: Trip to Dharamsala [Lowell Thomas and the Dalai Lama], circa 1963; 10 (Box 1536)
    - [Lowell Thomas and a monk], 1
    - [Lowell Thomas, a monk, and an unidenitified man], 2
    - [Lowell Thomas, a monk, and a man with a dog], 3
    - [Lowell Thomas, a monk, and a dog], 4
    - [Lowell Thomas petting a dog with a monk and another man], 5
    - [Lowell Thomas and three men looking at a map], 6
    - [Lowell Thomas looking at a man with three men], 7
  - Tibet: Trip to Dharamsala [Lowell Thomas and Tsering Dolma, eldest sister of the Dalai Lama], circa 1963; 11 (Box 1536)
    - [Lowell Thomas and a group of people in Tibet], 1
    - [Lowell Thomas and a group of children in Tibet], 2
    - [Lowell Thomas and a group of Tibetan children], 3
    - [Lowell Thomas standing by a group of children in Tibet], 4
    - [Lowell Thomas and two women in Tibet], 5
    - [Lowell Thomas and a line of children in Tibet], 6
    - [Lowell Thomas and a group of children in Tibet], 7
    - [Woman surrounded by children], 8
    - [Children playing on a playground in Tibet], 9
    - [Children on see-saws in Tibet], 10
    - [Children on see-saws in Tibet], 11
    - [Tibetan children playing on a see-saw], 12
    - [Lowell Thoams watching children play in Tibet], 13
    - [Children playing on the ground in Tibet], 14
    - [Tibetan children on swings], 15
    - [Children in Tibet playing on swings], 16
    - [Children dancing in Tibet], 17
    - [Children in Tibet dancing], 18
    - [Line of children in Tibet holding hands], 19
    - [Tibetan girls and boys dancing], 20
    - [Children dancing in Tibet], 21
    - [Lowell Thomas at the Tibetan refugee nursery], 22
    - [Children outside of the Tibetan refugee nursery], 23
    - [Children who reside at the Tibetan refugee nursery], 24
    - A group of Tibetan woman repairing roads in the Himalayan mountains in North India. Damage resulted from mountain snow-slides during December which trapped hundreds of Indians and Tibetan refugees., 25
    - Verso: A group of Tibetan woman repairing roads in the Himalayan mountains in North India. Damage resulted from mountain snow-slides during December which trapped hundreds of Indians and Tibetan refugees., 25-verso
    - A group of Tibetan refugees now encamped on the ouskirts of Delhi. They are refugees for the second time, having recently been evacuated from N.E.F.A. In the backgroung may be seen the adjacent Buddhist shrine and monestary., 26
    - Verso: A group of Tibetan refugees now encamped on the ouskirts of Delhi. They are refugees for the second time, having recently been evacuated from N.E.F.A. In the backgroung may be seen the adjacent Buddhist shrine and monestary., 26-verso
    - Part of a group of 300 refugees who have recently arrived at Pathancot in northern India. One half of them were evacuated from NEFA during the invasion of India by Cooounis China. The others have come from Nepal where there are more than 20,000 Tibetan refugees. When asked why they had come to India they said there were neither food nor jobs in Nepal and they had been informed that the Chinese would strike there next., 27
    - Verso: Part of a group of 300 refugees who have recently arrived at Pathancot in northern India. One half of them were evacuated from NEFA during the invasion of India by Cooounis China. The others have come from Nepal where there are more than 20,000 Tibetan refugees. When asked why they had come to India they said there were neither food nor jobs in Nepal and they had been informed that the Chinese would strike there next., 27-verso
    - [Lowell Thomas and two women at the Tibetan refugee nursery], 28
  - Tibet: Trip to Dharamsala [Lowell Thomas and Heinrich Harrer], circa 1963; 12 (Box 1536)
    - Note: Henrich [Heinrich] Harrer taught Dalai Lama English, 1
    - L.T. and Heinrich Harrer, "7 years in Tibet", 2
    - Verso: L.T. and Heinrich Harrer, "7 years in Tibet", 2-verso
    - L.T. and Heinrich Harrer, 3
    - L.T. and Heinrich Harrer, 4
    - L.T. and Heinrich Harrer, 5
    - L.T. and Heinrich Harrer, 6
    - L.T. and Heinrich Harrer, 7
  - Tibet: Trip to Dharamsala [Travis L. Fletcher and Katherine Cantwell], circa 1963; 13 (Box 1536)
    - The Director [Travis L. Fletcher] and his associate Mrs. Katherine Cantwell are greeted by the children at the Tibetan Nursery School in Dharamsala on the occasion of a recent visit. The usual salutation of the Bhudists [Buddhists] is in evidence. The sister [Tsering Dolma] of His Holiness stands to the right of Mr. Fletcher. She directs the work of this school which accommodates 600 children. AECTR [American Emergency Committee for Tibetan Refugees] has supported the nursery with medecines [sic], clothing, shoes and food, just one of four schools receiving similar help, 1
    - Verso: The Director [Travis L. Fletcher] and his associate Mrs. Katherine Cantwell are greeted by the children at the Tibetan Nursery School in Dharamsala on the occasion of a recent visit. The usual salutation of the Bhudists [Buddhists] is in evidence. The sister [Tsering Dolma] of His Holiness stands to the right of Mr. Fletcher. She directs the work of this school which accommodates 600 children. AECTR [American Emergency Committee for Tibetan Refugees] has supported the nursery with medecines [sic], clothing, shoes and food, just one of four schools receiving similar help, 1-verso
    - Mrs. Katherine Cantwell, Assistant Field Director, AECTR [American Emergency Committee for Tibetan Refugees], with one of hundreds of Tibetan women who were recently evacuated from NEFA during the invasion of India by Communist China. Though depressed and disillusioned the Tibetans never complain, witness the happy expression on this woman's face. This photograph was taken in the Kulu valley in the far northern part of India where AECTR [American Emergency Committee for Tibetan Refugees] is furnishing medecines [sic] and other relief supplies, 2
    - Verso: Mrs. Katherine Cantwell, Assistant Field Director, AECTR [American Emergency Committee for Tibetan Refugees], with one of hundreds of Tibetan women who were recently evacuated from NEFA during the invasion of India by Communist China. Though depressed and disillusioned the Tibetans never complain, witness the happy expression on this woman's face. This photograph was taken in the Kulu valley in the far northern part of India where AECTR [American Emergency Committee for Tibetan Refugees] is furnishing medecines [sic] and other relief supplies, 2-verso
    - T.L.F. [Travis L. Fletcher] and K.K.C. [Katherine Cantwell] were greeted by the children at the nursery in Dharamsala with songs and dances of their native country, 3
    - Verso: T.L.F. [Travis L. Fletcher] and K.K.C. [Katherine Cantwell] were greeted by the children at the nursery in Dharamsala with songs and dances of their native country, 3-verso
    - K.K.C. [Katherine Cantwell] is greeted by a group of children at the nursery school for Tibetan refugees in Dharamsala, 4
    - Verso: K.K.C. [Katherine Cantwell] is greeted by a group of children at the nursery school for Tibetan refugees in Dharamsala, 4-verso